<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The charter of the city of New-York</title>
            <title>Charter (1686)</title>
            <author>New York (N.Y.).</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53029</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N828</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC W18936</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13574959</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13574959</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100432</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53029)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100432)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 797:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The charter of the city of New-York</title>
                  <title>Charter (1686)</title>
                  <author>New York (N.Y.).</author>
                  <author>Limerick, Thomas Dongan, Earl of, 1634-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>William Bradford,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[New York :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Charter granted by Governor Thomas Dongan; the charter, which became known as Dongan's Charter, was virtually effective on Dec. 10, 1683, although it did not receive official seal of the province until Apr. 27, 1686.  Cf. Encyc. Amer., 1977, v. 20, p. 237.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>New York (N.Y.) --  Charters.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="charter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100432:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE CHARTER OF THE <hi>City of New-York.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Dongan</hi> Lieutenant Governour &amp; Vice Admiral of <hi>New-York</hi> and its Dependencies, under his Majeſty <hi>James</hi> the ſecond, by the Grace of God, of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland,</hi> King, Defendor of the Faith, ſupream Lord &amp; Proprietor of the Collony &amp; Province of <hi>New-York,</hi> and its Dependencies in <hi>America,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </argument>
            <salute>To all to whom this shall come, ſendeth Greeting.</salute>
            <p>WHEREAS the City of <hi>New-York</hi> is an antient City within the ſaid Province, and the Citizens of the ſaid City have antienly been a Body Politick and Corporate. And the Citizens of the ſaid City have held, uſed and enjoyed, as well within the ſame, as elſe-where within the ſaid Province, divers and ſundry Rights, Liberties, Priviledges, Francheſes, Free Cuſtoms, Preheminences, Advantages, Juriſdictions, Emoluments and Immunities, as well by Preſcription, as by Charter, Letters Patents, Grants and Confirmations, not only of divers Governors and Commanders in Chief in the ſaid Province, but alſo of ſeveral Governours, Directors, Generals and Commanders in Chief of the <hi>Nether-Dutch-Nation,</hi> whilſt the ſame was or has been under their Power and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. And whereas divers Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments Juriſdictions, Liberties, Immunities and Priviledges have heretofore been given and granted, or mentioned to be given &amp; granted to the Citizens and Inhabitants of the ſaid City, ſometimes by the name of <hi>Schout Burger maſters &amp; Schepens of the City of New-Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> &amp; ſometimes by the Name of <hi>Mayor, Alder-men &amp; Commonalty of the City of New-York;</hi> ſometimes by the Name of the <hi>Mayor, Aldermen &amp; Sheriff of the City of New-York;</hi> ſometimes by the Name of <hi>the Mayor &amp; Aldermen of the City of New-York,</hi> and by divers other Names, as by their ſeveral Letters Patents, Charters, Grants,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100432:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>Writings, Records and Minuments amongſt other things may more fully appear. And wheras the Citizens and Inhabitants of the ſaid City have erected, built and appropriated, at their own proper Coſts &amp; Charges, ſeveral publick Buildings, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations and Conveniences for the ſaid City, That is to ſay, the City-Hall or Stat-houſe, with the Ground thereunto belonging, Two Market-houſes, the Bridge into the Dock, the Wharffs or Dock, with their appurtenances and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, and the New Burial-place without the Gate of this City, and have eſtabliſhed and ſettled one Ferry from the ſaid City of <hi>New-York</hi> to <hi>Long-Iſland,</hi> for the accommodation and conveniency of Paſſengers, the ſaid Citizens and Travellers.</p>
            <p>And whereas ſeveral the Inhabitants of the ſaid City and of <hi>Manhattans Iſland,</hi> do Hold from and under his moſt Sacred Majeſty reſpectively, as well by ſeveral reſpective Letters Patents, Grants, Charters and Conveyances, made and granted by the late Leiutenants, Governours or Commanders in Chief of the ſaid Province, as otherwiſe, ſeveral and reſpective Meſſuages, Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments upon <hi>Manhattans Iſland,</hi> and in the City of <hi>New-york</hi> aforeſaid, and that as well the ſaid Mayor and Aldermen, and Commonalty of the ſaid City, and their Succeſſors, as alſo the Inhabitants of <hi>Manhattens Iſland</hi> and <hi>City of New-York</hi> aforſaid, as their Heirs and Aſſigns reſpectively, may hold, exerciſe and enjoy ſuch and the ſame Liberties, Privile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ges and Franchiſes, Rights, Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties, free Cuſtoms, Juriſdictions and Immunities, as they have antiently had, uſed, held and enjoyed, but alſo ſuch publick Buildings. Accommodations, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venienciès, Meſſuages, Tenements, Lands and Hereditaments in the ſaid City of <hi>New-york,</hi> and upon <hi>Manhattans Iſland</hi> aforſaid, which as above-ſaid, have been by the Citizens and Inhabitants erected and built, or which have, as aforſaid, been held, enjoyed, granted and conveyed unto them, or any of them reſpectively.</p>
            <p>Know Ye therefore, That <hi>I</hi> the ſaid <hi>Thomas Dungon,</hi> by virtue of the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Authority to me given, and Power in me reſiding, at the humble Petition of the now Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the ſaid City of <hi>New-york,</hi> and for divers other good Cauſes and Conſiderations me thereunto moving, have given, granted, ratified and confirmed, and by theſe Preſents, for and on the behalf of his moſt ſacred Majeſty aforeſaid, his Heirs, Succeſſors and Aſſigns, do give, grant, ratifie and confirm unto the ſaid Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the ſaid City, All and every ſuch, and the ſame Liberties, Priviledges, Franchiſes, Rights, Royalties, Free Cuſtoms, Juriſdictions and Immunities, which they by the Name of the Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty, or otherwiſe, have antiently had, held, uſed or enjoyed. Provided always, That none of the ſaid Liberties, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, Franchiſes, Rights, Free Cuſtoms, Juriſdictions or Immunities be inconſiſtent with, or Repugnant to the Laws of his Majeſties Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or any other the Laws of the General Aſſembly of this Province. And the aforeſaid publick buildings, accommodations and Conveniences in the ſaid City, that is to ſay, the aforeſaid City Hall or State-Houſe, with the ground thereunto belonging<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> two Market Honſes, the Bridge into the Dock, the Wharffs or Dock, the ſaid New Burial-Place, and the afore-mentioned Ferry, with their, &amp; every of their Rights, Members &amp; Appurtenances, together with all the profits, benefits &amp; advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, which ſhall or may accrew or ariſe at all Times hereafter, for Dockage or Wharfage within the ſaid Dock, with all &amp; ſingular the Rents, Iſſues, Profits, Gains and Advantages, which ſhall or may ariſe, grow or accrue, by the ſaid City Hall or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100432:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtate-Houſe, and ground there-unto belonging, Market Houſes, Bridge, Dock and Burying place, Ferry, &amp; other the above-mentioned premiſſes, or any of them. And alſo all and every the Streets, Lanes, High-Ways &amp; Allyes within the ſaid City of <hi>New-York</hi> and <hi>Manhattans Iſland</hi> aforeſaid, for the publick uſe and ſervice of the ſaid Mayor, Aldermen &amp; Commonalty of the ſaid City, the Inhabitants of <hi>Manhattans Iſland</hi> aforeſaid, &amp; Travellers there; together with full Power, Licence and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to the ſaid Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty, and their Succeſſors forever, To eſtabliſh, appoint, order and direct the eſtabliſhing making, ordering, amending, repairing &amp; laying out of all Streets, Lanes, Alleys, High-wayes, Water-Courſes, Ferry and Bridges in and throughout the ſaid City of <hi>New-York</hi> and <hi>Manhattans Iſland</hi> aforeſaid, neceſſary, needful and convenient for the Inhabitants of the ſaid City and <hi>Manhattans Iſland,</hi> and for all Travellers and Paſſengers there. Provided alwayes, that this ſaid Licence, ſo as above granted for the eſtabliſhing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and laying out of Streets, Lanes, Alleys, High-wayes, Ferry and Bridges<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be not extended, or be conſtrued to extend to the taking away of any Perſon or Perſons Right or Property, without his, her or their Conſent, or by ſome known Law of the ſaid Province.</p>
            <p>And for the Conſiderations aforeſaid, I do likewiſe Give, Grant, Ratifie and Confirm unto all and every the reſpective Inhabitants of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> and of <hi>Manhattans Iſland</hi> aforeſaid, and their ſeveral reſpective Heirs and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, All and every the ſeveral and reſpective Meſſuages, Tenements, Lands and Hereditaments ſcituate, lying and being in the ſaid City &amp; <hi>Manhattans Iſland</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, to them ſeverally and reſpectively granted, conveyed and Confirmed by any of the late Governours, Lieutenants, or Commanders in Cheif of the ſaid Province, or by any of the former Mayors or Deputy Mayor and Aldermen of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> by Deed, Grant, Conveyance, or otherwiſe howſoever, To hold to their Several and Reſpective Heirs and Aſſigns forever.</p>
            <p>And I do by theſe Preſents Give and Grant unto the ſaid Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> All the Waſte, Vacent, Unpatented &amp; Unappropriated Lands, lying and being within the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> and on <hi>Manhattens Iſland,</hi> as aforeſaid, extending and reaching to the Low-Water-Mark in, by and through all Parts of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York and Manhattans Iſland,</hi> as aforeſaid; To gether with all Rivers, Rivolets, Coves, Creeks, Ponds, Water, Water-courſes in the ſaid City and Iſland, or either of them, not heretofore given or granted by any of the former Governors, Lieutenants or Commanders in chief, under ſome of their hands and Seals, or Seal of the Province, or by any of the former Mayors or Deputy Mayors and Aldermen of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> to ſome reſpective Perſon or Perſons, late Inhabitants of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> or <hi>Manhattans Iſland,</hi> or other parts of the ſaid Province. And I do by theſe preſents Give, Grant and Confirm unto the ſaid Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> and their Succeſſors forever, the Royalties of Fiſhing, Fowling, Hunting, Hawking, Mineral and other Royalties and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges belonging or Appertaining to the City of <hi>New-York,</hi> and <hi>Manhattans Iſland,</hi> aforeſaid (Gold and Silver Mines only excepted) To Have, Hold, and Enjoy all and ſingular the Premiſes to the ſaid Mayor, Alder-men and Commonalty of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> and their Succeſſors forever, Rendering and paying therefor unto his Moſt Sacred Majeſty, his Heirs, Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors or Aſſigns, or to ſuch Officer or Officers, as ſhall be appointed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100432:3"/>the ſame yearly forever hereafter, the annual Quit-Rent or Acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of one Beaver Skin, or the value thereof in Currant Money of this Province, in the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> on the 25th day of <hi>March</hi> yearly forever. And moreover, I will, and by theſe preſents do grant, appoint and declare, that the ſaid City of <hi>New-York</hi> and the Compaſs, Precincts and Limits thereof, and the Juriſdiction of the ſame, ſhall from henceforth extend to reach it ſelf, and may &amp; ſhall be able to reach forth and extend it ſelf, as well in length and in breadth, as in Circuit, to the furtheſt extent of and in and throughout all the ſaid <hi>Iſland Manhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> and in and upon all the Rivers, Rivolets, Coves, Creeks, Water and Water Courſes, belonging to the ſaid Iſland, as far as low water mark. And I Do alſo for and on the behalf of His moſt ſacred Majeſty aforeſaid, his Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, firmly enjoyn and Command, That the afore-ſaid Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the City aforeſaid, and their ſucceſſors, ſhall and may freely and quietly Have, Hold, Uſe and enjoy the aforeſaid Liberties, Authorities, Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Franchiſes, Rights, Royalties, Priviledges, Exemptions, Lands, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements, Hereditaments and Premiſſes aforeſaid, in manner and form aforeſaid, according to the tenor and effect of thè aforeſaid Grants, Patents, Cuſtoms and Letters Patents of Grants and Confirmation, without the Let, Hinderance or Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment of me or any of my Succeſſors, Governours, Lieutenants, or other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers whatſoever. And alſo I do for, and on the behalf of his Moſt Sacred Majeſty aforeſaid, his Heirs and Succeſſors, Grant to the Mayor, Aldermen and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York</hi> and their Succeſſors, by theſe preſents, That for the better Government of the ſaid City, liberties and precincts thereof, There ſhall be forever hereafter, within the ſaid City, A Mayor and Recorder, Town Clerk, and ſix Aldermen, and ſix Aſſiſtants, To be appointed, nominated, elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, choſen and Sworn, as herein after is particularly and reſpectively mentioned, who ſhall be forever hereafter called, <hi>The Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the City of New-York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that there ſhall be forever one Chamberlain or Treaſurer, one Sheriff one Coroner, one Clerk of the Market, one High Conſtable, Seven Sub Conſtables, and one Marſhal or Serjant at Mace, To be appointed, choſen and Sworn in manner hereafter mentioned. And I do by theſe preſents, for and on the behalf of his Moſt Sacred Majeſty aforeſaid, his Heirs, Succeſſors and Aſſigns, Declare, Conſtitute, Grant and Appoint, That the Mayor, Recorder, Aldermen and Aſſiſtants of the ſaid City of <hi>New York</hi> for the time being, and they which hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall be the Mayor, Recorder and Aldermen and Aſſiſtants of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York</hi> for the time being, and their Succeſſors forever hereafter, be and ſhall be, by force of theſe preſents, one Body Corporate and Politick, in deed, fact and name, by the name of the <hi>Mayor, Aldermen</hi> &amp; <hi>Commonalty of the City of New-york;</hi> and them by the name of the Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the City of <hi>New-York</hi> one Body Corporate &amp; Politick in deed, fact &amp; name, I do really &amp; fully create, ordain, make, Conſtitute and Confirm by theſe preſents. And that by the Name of the Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> they may have perpetual ſucceſſion, and that they and their Succeſſors forever, by the Name of Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the City of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ew-York,</hi> be and ſhall be forever hereafter, Perſons able and in Law, capable, to have, get, receive and poſſeſs Lands, Tenements, Rents, Liberties, Juriſdictions, Franchiſes and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments to them and their Succeſſors in ſee ſimple or for term of Life, Lives or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100432:3"/>years, or otherwiſe; and alſo Goods and Chattels, and alſo other things of what nature, kind or quality ſoever, and alſo to give, grant, let, ſet and aſſign the ſame Lands, Tenements, Hereditamants, Goods and Chattles, and to do and execute all other things about the ſame by the name aforeſaid. And alſo, that they be, and forever ſhall be hereafter, Perſons able in Law, capable to plead and be impleaded, anſwer &amp; be anſwered unto, defend &amp; be defended, in all or any the Courts of his ſaid Majeſty, and other places whatſoever, and before any Judges, Juſtices and other perſon or perſons whatſoever, in all &amp; all manner of <hi>actions ſuits, complaints, demands, pleas, cauſes</hi> &amp; <hi>matters whatſoever,</hi> of what nature, kind or quality ſoever, in the ſame, and in the like manner and form as other People of the ſaid Province, being Perſons able, and in Law capable, may plead and be impleaded, anſwer and be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto, defend and be defended by any lawfull wayes and means whatſoever. And that the ſaid Mayor Aldermen and Commonalty of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> and their Succeſſors ſhall and may forever hereafter, have one common Seal to ſerve for ſealing of all and ſingular their affairs and buſineſſes, touching and concerning the ſaid Corporation. And I ſhall and may be lawfull to and for the ſaid Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> and their Succeſſors, as they ſhall ſee cauſe to break, change, alter and New make their ſaid Common Seal when and as often as to them it ſhall ſeem convenient.</p>
            <p>And further, know ye, That I have Aſſigned Named, Ordained &amp; Conſtituted, and by theſe preſents do aſſign, name, ordain and conſtitute <hi>Nicholas Bayard</hi> now Mayor of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York</hi> to be preſent Mayor of the ſaid City, and that the ſaid <hi>Nicholas Bayard</hi> ſhall Remain and continue in the Office of Mayor there, until another ſit Perſon ſhall be appointed and ſworn in the ſaid Office, according to the uſage and Cuſtom of the ſaid City, as in and by theſe preſents is hereafter mentioned and directed. And I have aſſigned, named, ordained and Conſtituted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by theſe preſents do aſſign, name, ordain and Conſtitute, Create and Declare <hi>James Graham,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> to be the preſent Recorder of the ſaid City, To do and execute all things which unto the Office of Recorder of the ſaid City doth or may in any wiſe appertain or belong. And I have aſſigned, named, ordained and conſtituted, and by theſe preſents do aſſign, name, ordain, conſtitute create and declare <hi>John Weſt,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Town Clerk of the ſaid City, To do and execute all things which unto the Office of Town-Clerk may any wiſe appertain or belong. And I have named, aſſigned, conſtituted and made, and by theſe preſents do Aſſign, Name, conſtitute &amp; make <hi>Andrew Bown, John Robinſon, William Beakman, John Delavall, Abraham Depyſter</hi> and <hi>Johannes Kipp,</hi> Citizens and Inhabitants of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> to be the preſent Aldermen of the ſaid City. And alſo I have made, aſſigned, named and conſtituted, and by theſe Preſents do aſſign, name, conſtitute and make <hi>Nicholas Demeyer, Johannes van Brugh, John de Brown, Thenniſs de Key, Abraham Corbit</hi> and <hi>Wolfert Wobber,</hi> Citizen and Inhabitants of the ſaid City, to be the preſent Aſſiſtants of the ſaid City. And alſo, I have aſſigned, choſen, Named and Conſtituted and by theſe preſents do Aſſign, Chooſe, Name and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute <hi>Peter Delanoy,</hi> Citizen and Inhabitant of the ſaid City to be the preſent Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain or Treaſurer of the City aforeſaid. And I have Aſſigned, Named, Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted and Appointed, and by theſe preſents do aſſign, name, conſtitute and appoint <hi>John Knight,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> another of the ſaid Citizens there, to be preſent Sheriff of the ſaid City. And have aſſigned, named and appointed, and by theſe preſents do aſſign Name, Conſtitute and appoint <hi>Jarvis Marſhall,</hi> another of the ſaid Citizens there,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100432:4"/>to be preſent Marſhall of the ſaid City. And I do by theſe preſents Grant to the ſaid Aldermen and Commonalty of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York</hi> and their Succeſſors, That the Mayor, Recorder, Aldermen and Aſſiſtants of the ſaid City, for the time being, or the Mayor, Recorder, or any three or more of the Aldermen, and any three or more of the Aſſiſtants for the time being, Be and ſhall be called, <hi>The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Council of the ſaid City;</hi> And that they, or the greater part of them, ſhall and may have full power and authority, by Virtue of theſe preſents, from time to time, To call and hold Common Council within the Common Council houſe, or City Hall of the ſaid City, and there, as occaſion ſhall be, to make Laws, Orders, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and Conſtitutions in writing, and to add, alter, diminiſh or reform them, from time to time, as to them ſhall ſeem neceſſary and Convenient, not repugnant to the Prerogative of his moſt Sacred Majeſty aforeſaid, his Heirs and Succeſſors, or to any of the Laws of the Kingdom of England, or other the Laws of the General Aſſembly of the Province of <hi>New-York,</hi> For the good Rule, Over-ſight, Correction and Goverment of the ſaid City and Liberties of the ſame, and of all the Officers thereof; And for the ſeveral Trades-men, Victuallers, Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and of all other the People and Inhabitants of the ſaid City, Liberties and Precincts aforeſaid; And for the better preſervation of Government, and diſpoſal of all the Lands, Tenements and Hereditaments, Goods and Chattels of the ſaid Corporation; which Laws, Orders, Ordinances &amp; Conſtitutions ſhall be binding to all the Inhabitants of the ſaid City, Libertyes and Precincts aforeſaid; And which Laws, Orders, Ordinances and Conſtitutions, ſo by them made as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, ſhall be and remain in force for the ſpace of three Moneths, and no longer, unleſs they ſhall be allowed of and confirmed by the Governor and Council for the time being. And I do further, on the behalf of his Sacred Majeſty aforeſaid, his Heirs and Succeſſors, appoint and grant, that the ſaid Common Council of the ſaid City for the time being, as often as they make, ordain &amp; eſtabliſh ſuch Laws, Orders, Ordinances and Conſtitutions, as aforeſaid, ſhall or may make, ordain, limit, provide, ſet, impoſe and tax reaſonable Fines &amp; Amerciaments againſt and upon all perſons offending againſt ſuch Laws, Orders, Ordinances and Conſtitutions, as aforeſaid, or any of them to be made, ordained and eſtabliſhed, as aforeſaid; &amp; the ſame Fines and Amercements, ſhall and may require, demand, levy, take and receive, by Warrant under the Common Seal, To and for the uſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoof of the Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the ſaid City, and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, either by diſtreſs and ſale of the Goods and Chattels of the Offendors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, if ſuch Goods and Chattles may be found within the ſaid City, Libertyes, and Precincts thereof, Rendering to ſuch offender and offenders the overplus, or by any other lawfull ways or means whatſoever. And I do by theſe preſents, Appoint and Ordain the aſſigning, naming and appointment of the Mayor, and Sheriff of the ſaid City, that it ſhall be as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> upon the Feaſt day of <hi>St. Michael,</hi> the Arch-angel, yearly, The Lieutenant Governour or Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Chief, for the time being, by and with the advice of the Council, ſhall nominate and appoint ſuch Perſon as he ſhall think fit, to be Mayor of the ſaid City, for the year next enſuing. AND one other Perſon, of ſufficient Ability and Eſtate, and of Good Capacity in underſtanding, to be Sheriff of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> for the year next enſuing. AND that ſuch perſons as ſhall be named, aſſigned and appointed Mayor, And ſuch Perſon as ſhall be named, aſſigned and appointed Sheriff of the ſaid city, as aforeſaid, ſhall on the fourteenth day of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100432:4"/>
               <hi>October</hi> then next following, take their ſeveral and reſpective Corporal Oathes Before the Governour and Council for the time being, for the due Execution of their reſpective Offices, as aforeſaid. And that the ſaid Mayor and Sheriff, ſo to be nominated, aſſigned and apointed, as aforeſaid, ſhall remain and continue in their ſaid reſpective Offices until another fit Perſon ſhall be nominated, appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſworn in the place of Mayor, and another perſon ſhall be nominated and appointed in the place of Sheriff of the ſaid City, in manner aforeſaid. And further, that according to the now uſage and Cuſtom of the ſaid City, the Recorder, Town Clerk &amp; Clerk of the Market of the ſaid City, ſhall be perſons of good Capacity and Underſtanding, and ſuch perſons as his moſt Sacred Majeſty aforeſaid, his heirs and ſucceſſors ſhall in the ſaid reſpective Offices of Recorder, Town-Clerk and Clark of the Market, appoint and commiſſionate; &amp;-for defect of ſuch ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments and comiſſionating by his Moſt Sacred Majeſty aforeſaid, his Heirs and Succeſſors. To be ſuch Perſons' as the Lieutenant Governours or Commanders in chief of the ſaid Province, for the time being, ſhall appoint and commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate; which Perſons, ſo Commiſſionated to the ſaid Offices of Recorder, Town Clerk &amp; Clerk of Market, ſhall have, hold and enjoy the ſaid Offices according to the tenor and effect of their ſaid Commiſſions, and not otherwiſe. And further, that the Recorder, Town Clerk and Clerk of the Market, Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Aſſiſtants, Chamberlain, High Conſtables, petty Conſtables, and all other Officers of the ſaid City, Before they, or any of them ſhall be admitted to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon and execute their reſpective Offices, ſhall be ſworn, <hi>faithfully to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute the ſame,</hi> before the Mayor, or any three, or more, of the Aldermen for the time being. And I do by theſe preſents, for and on the behalf of his Moſt ſacred Majeſty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his Heirs and Succeſſors, grant and give Power and Authority to the Mayor and Recorder of the ſaid City, for the time being, to adminiſter the ſame reſpective Oaths to them accordingly. And further, I do by theſe Preſents, grant, for and on the behalf of his Moſt Sacerd Majeſty aforeſaid, his Heirs and Succeſſors, that the Mayor and Recorder of the ſaid City for the time being, and three or more of the Aldermen of the ſaid City, not exceeding five, ſhall be Juſtices and Keepers of the Peace of his Moſt Sacred Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſors; And Juſtices to hear and determine matters or Cauſes within the ſaid City, and Libertyes, and Precincts thereof; and that they, or any three or more of them, whereof the Mayor and Recorder, or one of them, for the time being, to be there, ſhall and may forever hereafter, have Power and Authority, by virtue of theſe preſents, to hear and determine All and all manner of Petty La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyes, Riots, Routs, Oppre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ons, Extortions and other Treſpaſſes and Offences whatſoever, within the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> and the Liberties and Precincts afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid from time to time ariſing and happening, and which ariſe or happen, and any wayes belong to the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ces of the Juſtices of the Peace, and the Correction and puniſhment of the Offences aforeſaid, and every of them, according to the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> and the Laws of the ſaid Province; and to do and to execute all other things in the ſaid City, Liberties and Precincts aforeſaid, ſo fully and in ample manner, as to the Commiſſion aſſigned, and to be aſſigned, for the keeping of the Peace, in the ſaid County of <hi>New-York,</hi> doth or may belong. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, I do by theſe Preſents, for and in behalf of his Moſt Sacred Majeſty afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, his Heirs and Succeſſors, appoint, that the Aldermen, Aſſiſtants, high Conſtables and Petty Conſtables, within the ſaid City, be yearly choſen on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100432:5"/>the Feaſt day of <hi>St. Michael,</hi> the Arch Angel forever <hi>viz.</hi> one Alderman, one Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant and one Conſtable for each reſpective Ward, &amp; one Conſtable for each Diviſion in the out Ward, in ſuch Publick place in the ſaid reſpective Wards, as the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men for the time being for each Ward, ſhall direct and appoint. And that the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, Aſſiſtants and petty Conſtables be choſen by the Majority of Voices of the Inhabitants of each Ward. And that the High Conſtable be appointed by the Mayor of the ſaid City, for the time being. And that the Chamberlian ſhall be yearly Choſen on the ſaid Feaſt day, in the ſaid City-Hall in the ſaid City, by the Mayor, Aldermen and Aſſiſtants, or by the Mayor, or three or more of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, and three or more of the Aſſiſtants of the ſaid City for the time being. And I do by theſe preſents Conſtitute and appoint the ſaid <hi>John Weſt</hi> to be the preſent Town-Clerk, Clerk of the ſaid Peace, and Clerk of the Court of Pleas, To be holden before the Mayor, Recorder and Aldermen within the ſaid City, and Libertyes, and Precincts thereof. And further, I do by theſe Preſents, for and on the behalf of his Moſt Sacred Majeſty aforeſaid, his Heirs and Succeſſors, require, ſtrictly charge and Command, That the Sheriff, Town-Clerk, Clerk of the Peace, High Conſtable, Petty Conſtables, and all other Subordinate Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in the ſaid City, for the time being, and every of them reſpectively, joyntly and ſeverally, as cauſe ſhall require, ſhall attend upon the ſaid Mayor, Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Aldermen of the ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity for the time being, and every and any of them, according to the duty of the reſpective places, in and about the execution of ſuch the Commands, Precepts, Warrants and Proceſſes of them, and every of them, as belongeth &amp; appertaineth to be done or executed. And that the aforeſaid Mayor, Recorder, and Aldermen and every of them, as Juſtices of the Peace, for the time being, by their, or any of their Warrants, all and every Perſon or Perſons, for High Treaſon or Petty Treaſon, or for Suſpition thereof, or for other Fellonies whatſoever, and all Malefactors and Diſturbers of the Peace, and other Offenders, for other Miſdemeanors, who ſhall be apprehended within the ſaid City or Libertyes thereof, ſhall and may ſend and Commit, or cauſe to be ſent and Committed to the Common Goal of the ſaid City, There to remain and be kept in ſafe Cuſtody, by the Keepers of the ſaid Goal, or his Deputy for the time being, until ſuch Offender and Offenders ſhall Lawfully be delivered thence. And I do by theſe preſents, for and on the behalf of his Moſt Sacred Majeſty aforeſaid, his Heirs and Succeſſors, Charge and Require the keeper and keepers of the ſaid Goal, for the time being, and his and their Deputy and Deputyes to receive, take and in ſafe Cuſtody keep all and Singular ſuch Perſon and Perſons, ſo appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hened, or to be apprehended, ſent and Committed, to the ſaid Goal, by Warrant of the ſaid Juſtices, or any of them, as aforeſaid, until he and they ſo ſent and Committed to the ſaid Goal, from thence ſhall be delivered by due courſe of Law. And further, I do Grant and Confirm, for and on the behalf of his Moſt Sacred Majeſty aforeſaid, his Heirs and Succeſſors, That the ſaid Mayor of the ſaid City, for the time being, and no other according to the uſage and practice accuſtomed in the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> in the time of my Predeceſſors, the ſeveral Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, Governors and Commanders in Chief of this Province, ſhall have Power and Authority to give and Grant Liſences annually, under the publick Seal of the ſaid City, to all Tavern keepers, Inn-keepers, Ordinary-keepers, Victuallers, &amp; all Publick Sellers of Wine, Strong-Waters, Syder, Beer, or any other ſort of Liquors, by Retail within the City aforeſaid, <hi>Manhattaus Iſland,</hi> or their Liberties
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100432:5"/>and Precincts thereof. And it ſhall and may be lawfull to and for the ſaid Mayor of the ſaid City, for the time being, to ask, demand and receive for ſuch Liſence, by him to be given and granted, as aforeſaid, ſuch ſum or ſums of Money, as he and the Perſon to whom ſuch Liſence ſhall be given and granted, ſhall agree for, not exceeding the ſum of thirty ſhillings for each Liſence. All which Money, as by the ſaid Mayor, ſhall be ſo received, ſhall be uſed and applyed to the publick uſe of the ſaid Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> and their Succeſſors, without any account thereof to be rendered, made or done to any of the Lieutenants or Governours of this Province, for the time being, or any of their Deputies.</p>
            <p>AND Know ye, that for the better Government of the ſaid City, and for the wellfair of the ſaid Citizens, Trades-men and Inhabitants thereof, I do by theſe Preſents, for and in the behalf of his Moſt Sacred Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſors, Give and Grant to the ſaid Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the ſaid City, and their Succeſſors, That the Mayor, Recorder, and Aldermen, or the Mayor and any three or more of the Aldermen for the time being, ſhall from time to time, and at all times hereafter, have full Power and Authority, under the common Seal, make free Citizens of the ſaid City and Libertyes thereof, and no Perſon or Perſons whatſoever, other then ſuch free Citizens, ſhall hereafter uſe any Art, Trade, Myſtery, or manual Occupation, within the ſaid City, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes and Precincts thereof, ſaving in the time of Fairs only. And in caſe any Perſon or Perſons whatſoever, not being free Citizens of the ſaid City, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, ſhall at any time hereafter, uſe or Excerciſe any Art, Trade, Myſtery or manual occupation, or ſhall by himſelf, themſelves or others, ſell or expoſe to ſale any manner of Merchandize or Wares whatſoever by Retail in any Houſe, Shop, Place or Places, or Standing within the ſaid City, or the Liberties or Precincts thereof, no Fair being then kept in the ſaid City, and ſhall perſiſt therein, after warning to him or them given or left by the appointment of the Mayor of the ſaid City for the time being, at the place or places where ſuch Perſon or Perſons ſhall ſo uſe or exerciſe any Art, Trade or Myſtery, or manual Occupation, or ſhall ſell, or expoſe to ſale any Wares or Merchandize, as aforeſaid, by Retail, then it ſhall be lawful for the ſaid Mayor of the ſaid City, for the time being, to cauſe ſuch Shop Windows to be ſhut up, and alſo to impoſe ſuch reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Fine, for ſuch Offence, not exceeding five Pounds for every reſpective Offence; and the ſame Fine and Fines, ſo impoſed, to levy and take, by Warrant under the common Seal of the ſaid City, for the time being, by diſtreſs and ſale of the Goods and Chattels of the perſon or perſons ſo offending in the premiſes, found within the Liberties or Precincts of the ſaid City, rendring to the Party or Parties the over-plus, or by any other lawful ways or means whatſoever, to the only uſe of the ſaid Mayor, Alder-men and Commonalty of the ſaid City of New-York, and their Succeſſors, without any Account to be rendred, made or done to the Lieutenants, Governours or Commanders in chief of this Province, for the ſame. <hi>Provided,</hi> That no Perſon or Perſons ſhall be made free, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, but ſuch as are his Majeſties natural born Subjects, or ſuch as ſhall firſt be naturalized by Acts of General Aſſembly, or ſhall have obtained Letters of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nization, under the hand of the Lieutenant Governor or Commander in chief for the time being, and Seal of the Province; and that all Perſons to be made free, as aforeſaid, ſhall and do pay for the Publick Uſe of the ſaid Mayor,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100432:6"/>Aldermen and Commonality of the ſaid City, ſuch ſum and ſums of Money as heretofore hath been uſed and accuſtomed to be paid and received, on their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing admitted Free-men, as aforeſaid, provided it is not exceeding the ſum of five Pounds. And further, I do by theſe Preſents, for and on the behalf of his moſt ſacred Majeſty aforeſaid, his Heirs and Succeſſors, Grant to the Mayor, Aldermen and Commonality of the ſaid City, That they and their Succeſſors be forever Perſons able and capable, and ſhall have power to purchaſe, have, take and poſſeſs in fee ſimple, Lands, Tenements, Rents, and other Poſſeſſions within or without the ſame City, to them and their Succeſſors forever, ſo as the ſame exceed not the yearly value of One Thouſand Pound <hi>per annum,</hi> the Statute of <hi>Mortmain,</hi> or any other Law to the contrary notwithſtanding; and the ſame Lands, Tenements, Hereditaments and Premiſes, or any part thereof to demiſe, grant, leaſe, ſet over, aſſign and diſpoſe at their own will and pleaſure, and to make, ſeal and accompliſh any Deed or Deeds, Leaſe or Leaſes, Evidences or Writings, for or concerning the ſame, or any part thereof, which ſhall happen to be made and granted by the ſaid Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the ſaid City, for the time being.</p>
            <p>And further, I do by theſe preſents, for and on the behalf of his moſt ſacred Majeſty aforeſaid, his Heirs and Succeſſors, grant to the ſaid Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the ſaid City, That they and their Succeſſors, ſhall and may forever hereafter, hold and keep within the ſaid City, in every Weck of the Year, three Market days, the one upon <hi>Tueſday,</hi> the other upon <hi>Thurſday,</hi> and the other upon <hi>Saturday,</hi> weekly forever.</p>
            <p>And alſo, I do by theſe Preſents, for and on the behalf of his moſt ſacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, aforeſaid, his Heirs and Succeſſors, grant to the Mayor, Alder-men and Commonalty of the ſaid City, That they, and their Succeſſors and Aſſigns, ſhall and may at any time or times hereafter, when it to them ſhall ſeem fit and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, take in, fill and make up, and lay out all and ſingular the Lands and Ground in and about the ſaid City and Iſland <hi>Manhattaus,</hi> and the ſame to build upon, or make uſe of, in any other manner or way, as to them ſhall ſeem fit, as far into the Rivers thereof, and that encompaſs the ſame, as Low-water-mark aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And I do by theſe Preſents, for and on the behalf of his moſt Sacred Majeſty, aforeſaid, his Heirs and Succeſſors, give and grant unto the aforeſaid Mayor, Alder-men and Commonalty of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> and their Succeſſors, That they and their Succeſſors ſhall and may have, hold and keep within the ſaid City, and Liberties and Precincts thereof, in every Week, in every Year, forever, upon <hi>Tueſday,</hi> one Court of Common Pleas, for all Actions of Debt, Treſpaſs, and Treſpaſſes upon the Caſe, Detinue, Ejectment, and other Perſonal Actions, and the ſame to be held before the Mayor, Recordêr and Aldermen, or any three of them, whereof the Mayor or Recorder to be one, who ſhall have Power to hear and determine the ſame Pleas and Actions, according to the Rules of the common Law, and Acts of General Aſſembly of the ſaid Province.</p>
            <p>And I do by theſe Preſents, for and on behalf of his moſt ſacred Majeſty aforeſaid, his Heirs and Succeſſors, grant to the ſaid Mayor, Alder-men and Commonalty of the ſaid City of <hi>New-York,</hi> and their Succeſſors, That the ſaid Mayor, Aldermen and Commonalty of the ſaid City, and their Succeſſors, ſhall have and enjoy all the Priviledges, Franchiſes and Powers that they have
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100432:6"/>and uſe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ohany of their Predeceſſors at any time within the ſpace of twenty years laſt paſt, had, took and enjoyed, or ought to have had by reaſon, or under any pretence of any former Charter, Grant, Preſcription, or any other Right, Cuſtom or Uſage, although the ſame have been forfeited, loſt, or have been ill uſed, or not uſed, or abuſed, or diſcontinued, albeit they be not particularly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. And that no Officer ſhall diſturb them therein, under any pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, not only for their future, but their preſent enjoyment thereof. <hi>Provided always,</hi> That the ſaid Priviledges, Franchiſes and Powers be not inconſiſtent with or repugnant to the Laws of his Majeſties Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or other the Laws of the General Aſſembly of this Province, as afore-ſaid. And ſaving to his moſt ſacred Majeſty aforeſaid, his Heirs, Succeſſors and Aſſigns, and the Lieutenants, Governours and Commanders in chief, and other Officers under him and them in <hi>Fort James,</hi> in or by the City of <hi>New-York,</hi> and in all the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Boundaries, Extents and Priviledges thereof, for the maintenance of the ſaid Fort and Garriſon there, all the Rights, Uſe, Title and Authority which they, or any of them have had, uſed or exerciſed there, and alſo one Meſſuage or Tenement next the City Hall, and one Meſſuage by the Fort, now in the Poſſeſſion of <hi>Thomas Coker,</hi> Gent. the piece of ground by the Gate, called, The Governors Garden, and the Land without the Gate, called, the Kings Farm, with the Swamp next to the ſame Land, by the freſh Water. And ſaving the ſeveral Rents and Quit-Rents reſerved and due, and payable from ſevêral Perſons inhabiting within the ſaid City and Iſland <hi>Manhattans,</hi> by virtue of former Grants to them made and given. And ſaving to all other Perſons, Bodies Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick and Corporate, their Heirs, Succeſſors and Aſſigns, all ſuch Right, Title and Claim, Poſſeſſions, Rents, Services, common Emoluments and Intereſt in and to any thing which is theirs, ſave only the Franchiſes aforeſaid, in as ample manner as if this Charter had not been made.</p>
            <p>And further, I do appoint and declare, That the Incorporation to be founded by this Charter, ſhall not at any time hereafter do or ſuffer to be done any thing, by means whereof the Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments, Stock, Goods or Chattles thereof, or in the hands, cuſtody or poſſeſſion of any the Citizens of the ſaid City, ſuch as have been ſet, let, given, granted or collected to and for Pious and Charitable Uſes, ſhall be waſted or miſ-imployed, contrary to the Truſt or Intent of the Founder or Giver thereof, and that ſuch, and no other Conſtruction ſhall be made thereof, than that which may tend moſt to advantage Religion, Juſtice and the publick Good, and to ſuppreſs all Acts and Contrivances to be invented or put in uſe, contrary thereunto. <hi>IN WITNESS</hi> whereof I have cauſed theſe Preſents to be entered in the Secretary's Office, and the Seal of the ſaid Province to be hereto affixed this 27th day of <hi>April,</hi> in the ſecond Year of the Reign of his moſt ſacred Majeſty aforeſaid, and in the year of our Lord God, 1686.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Dongan.</signed>
            </closer>
            <closer>
</closer>
            <postscript>
               <opener>
                  <salute>May it pleaſe your Honour;</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe Attorney General hath peruſed this Patent, and finds nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein prejudicial to his Majeſties Intereſt.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Examined,</hi> 
                     <date>April 27. 1686.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Ja. Graham.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <postscript>
               <p>Recorded in the Secretary's Office for the Province of <hi>New-York,</hi> in Lib. No. 1. Book of Patents, begun 1684. from page 278. to 309.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. Spragge, <hi>Secry.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
